现在让我们制作 CSS 代码
Let's now make the CSS code
我们只是写得更好一点
that we just wrote a little bit better
通过组合一些选择器。
by combining some of the selectors.
所以你可能已经注意到
So you might've noticed
我们应用了完全相同的字体系列
that we applied the exact same font family
到我们这里的所有元素，对吧？
to all of our elements here, right?
所以我们在这里拥有的所有这六个 CSS 规则，
So all these six CSS rules that we have here,
它们都有字体样式，
all of them have font-style,
或者实际上将字体系列设置为无衬线字体。
or actually have font-family set to sans-serif.
你会看到 VS Code 实际上突出显示
And you see that VS Code actually highlights
这些出现在所有规则中。
these occurrences here in all of the rules.
所以这样做有点重复，对吧？
So doing that is a little bit repetitive, right?
这也不是一个好习惯
And it's also not a good practice
因为让我们说一下子
because let's say that all of a sudden
我们想将字体系列更改为其他内容。
we wanted to change the font-family to something else.
然后我们将不得不经历所有
Then we would have to go through all
这些不同的规则，然后设置字体系列
of these different rules and set the font-family then
到那里的别的东西。
to something else there.
所以与其，
So instead,
我们可以做的是创建一个选择器列表
what we can do is to create a list of selectors
为了选择多个元素
in order to select multiple elements
然后基本上将此字体系列应用于该列表。
and then apply this font-family to that list, essentially.
所以让我告诉你我们如何做到这一点
So let me show you how we can do that
实际上，让我们先在这里做。
and let's do it first here, actually.
所以我们要做的是选择h1元素
So what we want to do is to select the h1 element
和 h2 元素
and the h2 element
和 h3 元素。
and the h3 element.
如你所见，我们写它的方式
And so as you see, the way we write that
是通过使用这些逗号。
is by using these commas.
好的？
Okay?
再说一次，
So again,
在这里，我们将选择 h1 元素
here, we are going to select the h1 elements
和 h2 元素和 h3 元素
and the h2 elements and the h3 elements
和 h4 元素
and the h4 elements
和ps，
and the ps,
还有所有的 li 元素。
and also all the li elements.
好的。
Okay.
现在我们可以在这里抓取这个文本并剪切它
And now we can grab this text here and cut it
并将其粘贴在这里。
and paste it here.
现在我们可以将它从所有其他选择器中删除。
And now we can remove it from all of these other selectors.
好的。
All right.
如果我现在拯救它，
And if I give it a save now,
页面应该基本上看起来完全一样。
the page should basically look exactly the same.
它确实如此。
And it does.
好的，现在 Prettier 在这里像这样格式化了我们的 CSS 代码，
Okay, now Prettier formatted our CSS code here like this,
所以每一行都有一个元素，
so having one element for each line,
所以这更容易阅读。
and so this is a bit easier to read.
所以现在，如果我们想改变字体系列，
And so now, if we wanted to change the font-family,
让我们说衬线，这实际上是默认值。
let's say to serif, which is actually the default.
所以如果我现在保存这个，
So if I save this now,
然后您会看到所有元素同时发生了变化。
then you see that all of the elements changed at once.
所以他们现在都有衬线文本。
So all of them now have the serif text.
当然，如果我们把它放回这里，
Then of course, if we set it back here,
那么他们都会改变，对吗？
then all of them will change, right?
所以现在我们到处都有衬线文本。
So now we have serif text everywhere.
好吧，实际上，除了在页脚中。
Well, actually, except for in the footer.
所以这是我们需要解决的问题。
So that's something that we need to fix.
为了在这里更容易，
And to make it easier here,
让我们把这段文字简单地包装在这里
let's actually simply wrap this text here
段内。
inside a paragraph.
所以让我们来到我们的HTML。
So let's come here to our HTML.
所以你这样做真的很重要。
So this is really important that you do this.
所以在这里创建一个新元素
And so create a new element here
它会自动关闭它。
and it automatically closed it.
因此，让我们抓住这段文字并将其粘贴到此处。
So let's just then grab this text and paste it here.
你看现在这一段看起来
And you see that now this paragraph looks
就像所有其他人一样。
just like all the others.
好的？所以不要跳过这一步。
Okay? So don't skip this step.
请这样做，因为我们现在需要它
Please do this because we will now need it
再举一个例子。
for another example.
事实上，让我们马上来看这个例子。
And in fact, let's look at that example right away.
所以大小我们的段落是 22 像素。
So the size of our paragraphs is 22 pixels.
当然，现在页脚中的段落，
And so of course, now the paragraph that's in the footer,
所以这个，也是22像素。
so this one, is also 22 pixels.
但是，页脚中的文本
However, the text that's in the footer
通常比文本的其余部分小很多
is usually a lot smaller than the rest of the text
因为这只是一些次要信息
because this is just some secondary information
这并不重要。
that is not really important.
因此，我们实际上应该使这个文本
And so therefore we should actually make this text
在此段落中，此处小于文本
in this paragraph here smaller than the text
在其他段落中。
in the other paragraphs.
我们可以做到这一点的一种方法是组合选择器
And one way in which we can do this is to combine selectors
用另一种方式。
in another way.
回顾一下，这里我们结合了这六个选择器
So just to recap, here we combined these six selectors
到一个列表中。
into one list.
所以我们说这里的选择器现在是一个列表选择器。
So we say that the selector here is now a list selector.
所以这里仍然是一个选择器，
So this here is still one selector,
但它是一个列表选择器，好吗？
but it is a list selector, okay?
所以这是组合选择器的一种方式，
So this is one way of combining selectors,
但现在我会给你另一种组合选择器的方法
but now I will give you another way of combining selectors
正如我们刚刚讨论的那样，其目标是
and the goal of that is, as we just discussed,
在这里减小字体大小。
to decrease the font size in here.
所以我们现在将使用所谓的后代选择器，
So we will now use the so-called descendant selector,
也就是写这样的东西。
which is to write something like this.
所以我们选择页脚元素，
So we select the footer element,
然后是空格，然后是 p 选择器。
then a space, and then the p selector.
那么这会做什么
And so what this will do
是否会选择所有 p 元素
is it will select all the p elements
在页脚元素内部。
that are inside of footer elements.
这就是为什么这被称为后代选择器。
And so that's why this is called the descendant selector.
因为p元素是子元素
Because the p element is a child element
在我们的 HTML 中的页脚。
of the footer in our HTML.
因此，这里的选择器
And so therefore, this selector here
然后将选择所有这些段落
will then select all of these paragraphs
是页脚元素的子元素。
that are children of footer elements.
所以如果我们现在在这里设置字体大小
And so if we now set the font size here
到更小的东西，
to something smaller,
比方说16像素，
let's say 16 pixels,
然后你看到所有其他的ps，他们还是正常的，
then you see that all the other ps, they are still normal,
但实际上，在页脚里面的这段
but in fact, this paragraph that is inside the footer
现在只有 16 像素小。
is now only 16 pixels small.
希望你能看到它有多么有用
And hopefully you can see how useful
像这里这样的后代选择器是。
the descendant selector, like this here, is.
所以实际上一直使用它。
So actually use this all the time.
但是，在这种情况下，这实际上不是很健壮
However, in this case, this actually isn't very robust
因为，像这样，
because, like this,
选择器基本上反映了 HTML 结构，
the selector basically reflects the HTML structure,
这可能会导致问题。
which can lead to problems.
为了向你展示，
And to show that to you,
让我们再写一个后代选择器。
let's write another descendant selector.
所以在这种情况下，
So in this case,
假设我们要在这里选择这一段
let's say that we want to select this paragraph here
那是标题的内部。
that's inside of the header.
所以请记住，我们在文章中有一个标题，
So remember that we have a header here in the article,
所以这个在这里，我们有一个p。
so this one here, and we have a p.
假设我们想要设置斜体的样式，
So let's say we wanted to style that italic,
所以让文字斜体。
so make the text italic.
所以使用我们刚刚学到的，我们可以说标题，
And so using what we just learned, we could say header,
然后是里面的 p，
and then the p that is inside there,
然后说字体样式并将其设置为斜体。
and then say font-style and set it to italic.
好的，所以这工作得很好。
Okay, so this worked just fine.
但现在想象一下，出于某种原因，
But now imagine that, for some reason,
我们还在这个标题元素中添加了一个段落
we also added a paragraph to this header element
这是在页面中。
that is up here in the page.
所以让我们试试吧。
So let's try that.
请记住，这里还有另一个标题，对吧？
And remember that here we have another header, right?
所以正如我刚才所说，让我们在这里添加一个 p，
So as I was just saying, let's add a p here,
测试段，
Test paragraph,
你会看到这个现在也是斜体。
and you see that this one is now also italic.
然而，我们想要的只是这里的这一段
However, what we wanted was only this paragraph here
是斜体而不是这个，对吧？
to be italic and not this one, right?
所以我们需要以某种方式解决这个问题。
So we need to solve this somehow.
实际上我们可以解决它。
And actually we can solve it.
这不是太难。
It is not too hard.
好吧，至少在这种情况下，
Well, at least in this case,
因为这里的标题在文章里面
because this header here is inside of the article
而这个不是，对吧？
and this one is not, right?
所以我们实际上可以创建一个嵌套的后代选择器。
And so we can actually create a nested descendant selector.
所以我们可以在后代中有一个后代。
So we can have a descendant inside a descendant.
所以我的意思基本上是写这个。
So what I mean is basically writing this.
所以我们只想要标题内的段落，
So we only want the paragraphs that are inside of headers,
这是在文章的内部，是斜体。
which are inside of articles, to be italic.
所以让我们来拯救它。
So let's give it a save.
现在只有这个是斜体的
And now only this one is italic
而这个在这里，不再是。
and this one here, not anymore.
所以这实际上有效，
So this actually works,
但我们现在对 HTML 结构进行了更多编码
but we are now even more encoding the HTML structure
进入我们的 CSS 选择器，
into our CSS selectors,
这会使我们的代码在未来难以维护
and that can make our code hard to maintain in the future
如果我们改变了我们的 HTML。
if we ever change our HTML.
所以这不是一个好主意。
And so that's not a good idea.
因此，如果我们考虑这一点，
So if we think about this,
如果我们有办法真的会好很多吗
wouldn't it actually be a lot better if we had a way
基本上给一些元素名称
to basically give some elements names
然后使用这些名称来选择它们？
and then use these names to select them?
好吧，我们实际上可以做到这一点，
Well, we actually can do that,
这正是下一节课的主题。
and it is exactly the subject of the next lecture.
所以我们现在就去那里。
So let's go there right now.